A Guide to the VCU Gay Alliance of Students Collection, 1974-1976
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
VCU Gay Alliance of Students Collection, 1974-1976
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
M 357
.5 linear feet.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated in November of 2005 by Walter Foery a founder and the first student leader of the VCU Gay Student Alliance.
Historical Information
The Gay Alliance of Students (GAS) was founded as a student organization on September 1, 1974, at Virginia Commonwealth University in Richmond Virginia. GAS was organized to create a "unified support community for men and women of all sexual orientations, serve as an informative resource to the university and surrounding community, and assist the university in creating a positive institutional image by addressing and combating discrimination based on gender and sexual preference."
GAS was denied recognition as a student organization by the VCU Board of Visitors on October 17, 1974 on the grounds that the "existence of GAS as a recognized campus organization would tend to attract other homosexuals to the University." In October 1976, a civil case was brought to the U.S. District Court of Appeals Fourth District Circuit Court against VCU to allow for full funding and space allocations. The Federal Appeals Court ruled in favor of the student organization effectively changed existing law in ten southern states.
By the 1980s, the Gay Alliance of Students was known as the VCU Gay Student Alliance. As of 2010, there were two gay student organizations at VCU-the Sexual Minority Student Alliance and Queer Action.
Scope and Content
The collection was compiled by the donor, Walter Foery, a founding member of the VCU Gay Students Alliance organization. The materials in the collection help document the founding of the student organization at VCU, their efforts to be recognized by VCU as any other student organization, and the lawsuit initiated by the students. The items date from 1974 through 1976 and include correspondence, court documents, newspaper clippings, and magazines.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by file name.
Contents List
- Application for Registration as A Student Organization, Gay Alliance of Students, Initial and Final Copy 1974 (Box-folder 1:1)
- Conference Schedule-The Gay Academic Union, Third Annual Conference 1975 (Box-folder 1:2)
- Correspondence 1975-1976
  - The Advocate, Gregory Lewis, Editor 1975 (Box-folder 1:3)
    September 9, 1975, November 17, 1975
  - Blanton, Wyndham, Member of the VCU Board of Visitors, Clinical Professor of Medicine at the Medical College of Virginia November 20, 1975 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Byrd, Harry F., U.S. Senator August 5, 1975 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Foery, Walter A., Spokesperson Gay Alliance of Students November 2, 1975 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Lambda Legal Defense and Education fund Inc, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Lane, Lionel E., VCU School of Social Work March 6, 1976 (Box-folder 1:8)
  - McCarthy, John M., Attorney at Law, April 8, 1976 (Box-folder 1:9)
  - National Gay Task Force 1975-1976 (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Reynolds, Eddie, Director of Residence Education at Virginia Commonwealth University November 19, 1976 (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Scott, William L., U. S. Senator August 6, 1975 (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Tully, Carol, Social Worker, City of Richmond Department of Public Welfare, Social Service Bureau July 2, 1976 (Box-folder 1:13)
- Court Fee Payment Record, Gay Alliance of Students 1975-76 (Box-folder 1:14)
- Court Opinion, U.S. Court of Appeals Fourth District; Gay Alliance of Students, etc v. Alfred T. Matthews, et al 1976, Published and Unpublished Copies (Box-folder 1:15)
- Magazine Clippings, Time1975, 1979 (Box-folder 1:16)
- Memorandum, U.S. District Court, Eastern District of Virginia Richmond Division, Gay Alliance of Students etc, v., Alfred T. Matthews, et al 1975 (Box-folder 1:17)
- Newspaper Clippings, Gay Alliance of Students (GAS), Commonwealth Times and Flyer for GAS Sponsored Dance Event 1976 (Box-folder 1:18)
- Newspaper Clippings, Gay Alliance of Students, Commonwealth Times and Richmond Times-Dispatch1975 (Box-folder 1:19)
- Photography of Walter Foery undated (Box-folder 1:20)
- Press Releases, Gay Alliance of Students undated (Box-folder 1:21)
- Statement of Purpose, Draft and Final Copy, Gay Alliance of Students (GAS) and GAS Membership List undated (Box-folder 1:22)
- Subpoena for Taking Deposition, U.S. District Court, Eastern District of Virginia Richmond Division June 10, 1975 (Box-folder 1:23)
- Subpoena to Appear and Produce, U.S. District Court, Eastern District of Virginia Richmond Division June 10, 1975 (Box-folder 1:24)